Iwona Janicka

Curriculum Vitae

Researcher | Art History, Aesthetics & Culture, and Museology | Langelandsgade 139 | 8000 Aarhus, DK

Email: iwona.janicka@cantab.net | Webpages: Staff Profile AU | ORCID: 0000-0002-8433-9014

PROFILE

At the heart of my research lies the question of social transformation: How can we conceptualize and engage in politics that is relevant for the 21st century? Specifically, I focus on how politics is transformed in light of current climate change and rapid technological developments. In my work, I attempt to articulate a 'nonhuman politics', that is, politics for more-than-human worlds, in which questions of collective solidarity and alternative socio-political practices play an important part. By engaging with thinkers within broadly considered posthumanities and environmental philosophy, I hope to capture a series of transformations that are taking place in philosophy, art practices and in our cognitive maps of the world.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. French Studies, University of Cambridge, Trinity Hall, UK, 2014

Thesis title: Tribulations of Universality: Conceptualizing Slow Social Transformation with

Butler, Girard, Sloterdijk, and Badiou. Supervised by Ian James

M.Phil. European Literature and Culture (First Class), University of Cambridge, 2009

B.A. Literary Theory and Comparative Literature (with distinction), History of Art (minor),

Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München, Germany, 2008

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2019–2022	Assistant Professor EU Maria Skłodowska-Curie Actions COFUND II Fellow
	Aarhus Institute of Advanced Studies, Aarhus University, Denmark
2018–2019	Early Career Innovation Fellow, Institute of Advanced Study, University of Warwick, UK
2015-2018	British Academy Postdoctoral Fellow, French Studies, University of Warwick, UK

RESEARCH EXPERTISE

20th and 21st century French and German thought, Theory (Critical, Feminist, Queer, Anarchist, Posthuman), Literary Theory (Formalism, Structuralism, Poststructuralism, Narrative Theory)

LANGUAGES

Polish (native), English (fluent), French (fluent), German (fluent), Danish (advanced, C1 | *Studieprøven*), Russian (upper intermediate, B2), Czech (intermediate, B1)

FUNDING, FELLOWSHIPS & AWARDS (selected)

Thus far I have obtained a sum total nearing 700,000 € in external funding for my research projects as PI.

2022	The Carlsberg Foundation Conference Grant, Denmark
2018–2019	Early Career Innovation Fellowship Award, IAS, University of Warwick, UK
2015-2018	British Academy Postdoctoral Fellowship, University of Warwick, UK
2010–2014	Full PhD Scholarship from The Bill and Melinda Gates Cambridge Trust, UK
2009–2010	Scholarship Studienkolleg zu Berlin (Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes & Hertie), DE
2007-2008	Scholarship to study at Seoul National University, South Korea (DAAD & LMU München)

ORGANIZATION OF CONFERENCES & WORKSHOPS (selected)

Co-organizer for international conference in environmental philosophy

2022 "Earth Sensations: Affects, Sensibilities and Attachments in an Era of Climate Change" (with Tobias Skiveren), keynotes: Jane Bennett, Alexis Shotwell, Nicole Seymour, 13–14 October, AU, DK (funded by the Carlsberg Foundation, AIAS & Aarhus University)

Member of the organizing committee for international conference in French philosophy

2021 13th Annual Deleuze & Guattari Conference: "Territorialities, Exterritorialities, Non-Territorialities" (with Petr Kouba), keynotes: Etienne Balibar, Barbara Glowczewski and Eric Alliez, The Czech Academy of Sciences, Prague, July 5-7 (online with almost 200 speakers).

Principal organizer for international conference in posthumanism

2016 "Nonhumans and Politics. International Conference on Non-Anthropocentric Perspectives on Politics", funded and hosted by Forschungsinstitut für Philosophie Hannover, Jan. 22–23.

INVITED TALKS (selected)

2022	"What Universality? Cosmopolitics and its Guises", Becoming Planetary as a Challenge,
	Goethe-University, Frankfurt am Main, Germany, October 6-8.

- 2022 "Slow Social Transformation: How Radical Can It Get?" Global Klimaaktion, Aarhus, 13.4.
- 2019 "Designing Fictions: A Philosophical Perspective on Speculative Practices," Workshop *Designing Fictions*, Cultures, Spaces and Politics Research Group, School of Architecture, University of Sheffield, UK, February 18.
- 2017 "Ethics of Generosity, Gift Economy and Alternative Modes of Existence," *History, Genealogy, Archaeology: Alternative Approaches to Political and International Studies*, Kingston University London, UK, November 3.
- 2016 "Politics and Non-humans: Spherology and General Organology as Compasses for Political Practice?", *Welcome to the Anthropocene*. *Debate with Philosophers Peter Sloterdijk and Bernard Stiegler*, Expert seminar with Stiegler and Sloterdijk, Radboud University, Netherlands, June 27–28.

LIST OF PUBLICATIONS IWONA JANICKA

(All single-authored)

Monographs

 Theorizing Contemporary Anarchism. Solidarity, Mimesis and Radical Social Change (London and New York: Bloomsbury Academic, 2017) ISBN 9781474276191, 192 pages

Edited volumes

• Earth Sensations: Affects, Sensibilities and Attachments in an Era of Climate Change (ed. with Tobias Skiveren) in preparation for SubStance Special Issue

Journal articles with a peer review process

- "Paradoxes of Equality: Jacques Rancière's Politics and Nonhumans" (forthcoming in *Parrhesia: A Journal of Critical Philosophy*)
- "Reinventing the Diplomat: Isabelle Stengers, Bruno Latour and Baptiste Morizot" (forthcoming in *Theory, Culture & Society*)
- "Processes of Translation: Bruno Latour's Heterodox Semiotics." Textual Practice (2022), doi: 10.1080/0950236X.2022.2056765
- "Who Can Speak? Rancière, Latour and the Question of Articulation." *Humanities* 9.4 (2020): 123. doi.org/10.3390/h9040123
- "A New Way to Suffer: Girard, Rancière and Political Subjectification." *Contagion: Journal of Violence, Mimesis, and Culture* 26: Spring (2019), 161–78.
- "Über das Astronomische und das Mikroskopische: Sloterdijk und die Frage des Ausmaßes" [Scaling up, Scaling down: Sloterdijk and Grand Narratives], *Pro-Fil: An Internet Journal of Philosophy* (Special Issue, 2017), 18–23. Doi.org/10.5817/pf17-3-1647
- "Are These Bubbles Anarchist? Peter Sloterdijk's Spherology and the Question of Anarchism." *Anarchist Studies* 24.1 (2016), 62–84.
- "Queering Girard De-Freuding Butler. A Theoretical Encounter between Judith Butler's Gender Performativity and René Girard's Mimetic Theory." *Contagion: Journal of Violence, Mimesis, and Culture* 22 (2015), 43–64.
- "Homosocial Bonds and Narrative Strategies in Adolphe Belot's *Mademoiselle Giraud, ma femme* (1870)." *Romanica Silesiana. Gendered Constructions* 8 (2013), 138–150.
- "Hegel on a Carrousel: Universality and the Politics of Translation in the Work of Judith Butler." *Paragraph: A Journal of Modern Critical Theory* 36.3 (2013), 361–75.
- "Mapping the Father. The Application of Greimassian Semiotics to Bruno Schulz's *Sklepy Cynamonowe*." Welt der Slaven: Internationale Halbjahresschrift für Slavistik LV (2010), 45–66.

Chapters in edited volumes with a peer review process

 "Nonhuman Politics and its Practices." The Bloomsbury Handbook of Posthumanism, eds. Jacob Wamberg and Mads Rosendahl Thomsen, London and New York: Bloomsbury Academic (2020), 129– 140.

Encyclopedia entries

• "Anarchism." *Encyclopaedia of the Philosophy of Law and Social Philosophy*, eds. Mortimer Sellers, Stephan Kirste, Dordrecht: Springer (2023) doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-6730-0_1081-1

Submitted articles with a peer review process

• "The Janus Face of Cosmopolitics: Universality in Stengers and Latour" (for *Philosophy Today*)

Articles in preparation

- "Ecology and its Universals: Complicating Universality in an Age of Climate Change" (for *Environmental Humanities*)
- "Ecofeminists Strike Back! The Ecological Class and the Question of Social Reproduction" (for Ethics & Environment)

Book Reviews

- Carlos Taibo, Rethinking Anarchy: Direct Action, Autonomy, Self-Management (AK Press, 2018, translated by the Autonomous Collective), Anarchist Studies 30.2 (2022): 95-96. DOI: 10.3898/AS.30.2.REV.01
- Jon Asimakopoulos and Richard Gilman-Opalsky (eds.). Against Capital in Twenty-First-Century: A Reader of Radical Undercurrents (Philadelphia: Temple University Press, 2018), Anarchist Studies 28.1 (2020): 103. DOI:10.3898/AS.28.1.06
- Iain MacKenzie. *Resistance and the Politics of Truth. Foucault, Deleuze, Badiou* (Bielefeld: transcript-Verlag, 2018), *H-France Review* 20.163 (September 2020).
- Elettra Stimilli. *The Debt of Living: Ascesis and Capitalism*, translated by Arianna Bove, foreword by Roberto Esposito (New York: SUNY Press, 2017), *Journal of Italian Philosophy* 2 (2019): 114–17.
- Grace Hellyer and Julian Murphet (eds.). *Rancière and Literature* (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2016), *French Studies* 71.4 (2017): 610–11. doi.org/10.1093/fs/knx171
- Pierpaolo Antonello and Heather Webb (eds.). Mimesis, Desire, and the Novel. René Girard and Literary Criticism (East Lansing: Michigan State University Press, 2015), Modern Language Review 111.4 (2016): 1117–1118.
- David Scott. Gilbert Simondon: Psychic and Collective Individuation. A Critical Introduction and Guide (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2014), Notre Dame Philosophical Reviews, 2014.12.23

LIST OF SELECTED KEY PUBLICATIONS IWONA JANICKA

 Janicka, Iwona: "Reinventing the Diplomat: Isabelle Stengers, Bruno Latour and Baptiste Morizot" (accepted subject to minor revisions to *Theory, Culture & Society*)

The article traces the metamorphoses of the 'conceptual character' of the diplomat in the work of three contemporary thinkers of ecology: Isabelle Stengers, Bruno Latour and Baptiste Morizot. Its key contribution is to propose three new companion figures: the heretic (for Stengers), the designer (for Latour) and the amateur (for Morizot) that allow us to carefully examine the differences between, and the specific stakes of, each iteration of the diplomat. The article is important because it critically evaluates the theoretical pertinence of the diplomat figure for each philosopher's project, and considers its potential for thinking about alternatives futures of our more-than-human worlds.

■ Janicka, Iwona: "Processes of Translation: Bruno Latour's Heterodox Semiotics." *Textual Practice* (2022), doi: 10.1080/0950236X.2022.2056765

This article offers an in-depth analysis of the concept of translation in Bruno Latour's work – an ambiguous and constantly morphing term. It considers the various conceptual reformulations of translation throughout his writing, concentrating on its fundamental importance for the operation of his modes of existence (the AIME project). In this paper, I put a special emphasis on the influence of A. J. Greimas's semiotics on Latour's theoretical framework. I trace how translation is different from transformation, and why it remains a core concept in Latour's work, despite the fact that he strays far beyond the confines of linguistics alone in his theorisation. The article is important because it traces the structuralist heritage of Latour's project that has not been sufficiently examined in the discussions of his work and examines the potential of structuralism for thinking posthumanities.

Janicka, Iwona: "Who Can Speak? Rancière, Latour and the Question of Articulation." *Humanities* 9.4 (2020): 123. doi.org/10.3390/h9040123

This article instantiates a dialogue between Jacques Rancière and Bruno Latour on one of the fundamental questions of politics, that is, the question of *logos*. Even though Latour and Rancière differ considerably in their theoretical and political orientations, each of them revisits the question of "who can speak?" in order to examine the ways in which speechless entities gain a voice, thereby becoming intelligible as political entities. In this article, I confront Rancière's reservations about nonhumans as political agents, showing how Latour offers pathways beyond Rancière's apparent bias towards the human, a bias that is, I argue, fundamentally contradictory to the latter's broader conceptualization of politics as aesthetics. By combining Latour with Rancière I attempt to fundamentally rearticulate the parameters of left-wing politics with regard to nonhumans.

■ Janicka, Iwona: "Are These Bubbles Anarchist? Peter Sloterdijk's Spherology and the Question of Anarchism." *Anarchist Studies* 24.1 (2016), 62–84.

The question of solidarity is an important one for anarchism. However, to date solidarity as a concept has not been given the philosophical attention it deserves. The main contribution of this article is to fill in this gap in the anarchist literature and introduce a new concept of solidarity that originates in Peter Sloterdijk's work. I argue that Sloterdijk's concept allows for a theoretical support of the anarchist idea of slow, everyday transformation that is often contrasted with its main counter model for social change – revolution. Although not an anarchist himself, Sloterdijk nevertheless offers a theoretical framework to understand and constructively think about anarchism and contemporary anarchist movements. The article is important because it introduces a new concept of solidarity within radical left-wing thinking on politics and political practice.

Janicka, Iwona: "Queering Girard – De-Freuding Butler. A Theoretical Encounter between Judith Butler's Gender Performativity and René Girard's Mimetic Theory." Contagion: Journal of Violence, Mimesis, and Culture 22 (2015), 43–64.

This article responds to the fractional presence of feminist discourse around René Girard's theory of mimetic desire. It rehabilitates mimesis for feminism via an analysis of Judith Butler's theory of performative gender. The article's main contribution is to bring together the theories of Butler and Girard in order to explore new ways of thinking about gender. I show that the "failure" in mimesis, that is the constant approximation to the perfect imitation, guarantees unrestricted differentiation in gender. This combination of Girard and Butler aims to open up Girardian theory to exchanges with feminism, queer and transgender studies. Girard's theory of mimesis, in turn, offers Butler new possibilities for thinking about gender and identification. My claim is that the psychoanalytical framework that Butler draws upon is the cause of theoretical impasses that she encounters and that Girard's theory allows for overcoming these deadlocks.

 Janicka, Iwona, Theorizing Contemporary Anarchism. Solidarity, Mimesis and Radical Social Change (London and New York: Bloomsbury Academic, 2017) ISBN 9781474276191, 192 pages

The turn of the Millennium demonstrated a fully-fledged revival and fusion of various left-wing social movements with differing agendas. Movements for women's, black, indigenous, LGTB and animal liberation as well as ecological, anti-nuclear and anti-war groups unified against the global capital. Considering the diverse emphases of these movements, is there a philosophical framework that could help us understand their nature and their modes of operation in the 21st century? This book offers a set of new conceptual tools to do that. It proposes a theoretical model of 'slow' social transformation - a modality of social change that explicitly differs from the irruptive model of a revolution - and provides two concepts of 'mimetic contagion' and 'solidarity with singularity' which allow us to understand what is currently happening in the activist milieu. By bringing together some of today's most important thinkers, including Judith Butler, René Girard, Alain Badiou, and Peter Sloterdijk, this book suggests a philosophical lens to look at the alternative living projects that contemporary left-wing activists undertake in practice. At the heart of their projects lie the pressing concerns that these contemporary philosophers currently debate. Breaking from the conceptual apparatus of the Marxist tradition, *Theorizing Contemporary Anarchism* takes Hegelian concepts and feeds them through the thought of contemporary theorists in order to form an original, productive, and inclusive scaffold with which to understand today's world of social and political movements.